Let’s say you’re trying to
find some solid information
about a serious health
problem that concerns you,
like high blood pressure,
or diabetes.
Yet, everywhere you look,
someone’s trying to sell you
something like vitamins,
yoga mats, blenders, drugs.
Well, breathe a
sigh of relief
because all we bring
you are the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Does even thinking about migraines
give you a headache?
Well, you’re not alone.
Migraines affect an estimated 10 percent
of the population worldwide.
In our first story,
we put plant based diets to the test
for treating migraine disorders.
Headaches are one of the top five reasons
people end up in emergency rooms, and
one of the leading reasons for which
people see their doctors in general.
One of the things you
can try to do prevent them
is to identify the triggers
and avoid them.
Common triggers for migraines include
stress, smoke, hunger, sleep issues,
certain trigger foods like
chocolate, cheese, and alcohol,
your menstrual cycle, or
certain weather patterns.
In terms of dietary treatments,
the Father of Modern Medicine,
William Osler, suggested
trying a strict vegetable diet.
After all, the nerve inflammation
associated with migraines may be
reduced by a strictly plant-based
diet, as many plant foods are high
in anti-inflammatory compounds
and antioxidants, and likewise,
meat products may have
pro-inflammatory properties,
but it wasn't put to the test
for another 117 years.
Among those given a
placebo supplement,
half said they got better,
half said they didn't.
But when put on a strictly plant-based
diet they did much better,
experiencing a significant drop
in the severity of their pain.
Now it's possible that the pain reducing
effects of the plant-based diet
may have at least been in part,
due to the weight reduction;
they lost about 9 more pounds
in their vegan month.
Even just lowering the fat
content of the diet may help.
Those placed on a month of consuming
less than 30 grams of fat a day,
like less than two tablespoons
of oil all day, experienced highly
significant decreases in headache
frequency, intensity, duration,
and the need to take medications, a six-
fold decrease in frequency and intensity.
From three migraine attacks every
two weeks, down to just one a month.
And by low fat they didn't
mean SnackWell's;
they meant more fruits,
vegetables, beans.
Before the food industry co-opted
and corrupted the term,
eating low fat meant like eating
an apple, not Apple Jacks.
Now this was a really low-fat
diet, like 10% fat
for someone eating 2500 calories a day.
What about just less than 20% fat,
compared to a more normal, but still
relatively lower fat diet than average?
Same significant drops in headache
frequency and severity,
including a 5-fold drop in
attacks of severe pain.
Since the intervention involved at
least halving of saturated fat intake,
mostly found in meat, dairy, and junk,
the researchers concluded
that a reduction of saturated fat
intake may help control migraine
attacks, but it's not necessarily
something that they're getting less of.
There are compounds present
in live green real veggies
that might bind to a migraine-triggering
peptide known as CGRP.
Drug companies have been trying to
come up with something that binds to it,
but the drugs have failed to be
effective, and are also toxic,
a problem you don't see with cabbage.
Green vegetables also have magnesium,
found throughout the food supply
but mostly concentrated
in green leafy vegetables,
beans, nuts, seeds, and whole grains.
It's actually the central atom
to chlorophyll, so you can see
how much magnesium foods have
in the produce aisle by the
intensity of their green color.
Magnesium supplements do not appear
to decrease migraine severity,
but may reduce the number of
attacks you get in the first place.
You can ask your doctor about starting
600 mg of magnesium dicitrate every day,
but note, magnesium supplements can
cause adverse effects such as diarrhea,
so I recommend getting it
in the way nature intended.
Any foods that may particularly help?
I've talked about ground ginger.
Combining caffeine with over-the-counter
pain killers like Tylenol, aspirin and
ibuprofen may boost their
efficacy, about 130 milligrams
for tension-type headaches
and 100 mg for migraines,
about what you might expect to get
in three cups of tea, though I believe
it's just a coincidence that the
principle investigator was named Lipton.
Note you can overdo it. If you take
kids and teens who have headaches,
drinking one and a half liters of
cola a day, and cut the cola,
you can cure 90% of them, though
this may be a Coca-Cola effect
rather than a caffeine effect.
Did you know that daily
application of capsaicin
results in up to an 80% therapeutic
response rate for a certain type of headache?
Here’s the story.
It appeared worthwhile
to study the effects
produced by the topical
application of capsaicin
in the human nose.
It therefore appeared
worthwhile because
it had never been
done before? OK...
So they took some
medical students
dripped some
in their nose
and they started sneezing,
burning, and snotting.
Describing the pain as like 8 or 9
on a scale of 1 to 10.
No surprise, but here's
the interesting part.
What do you
think happened
when they repeated the
experiment the next day?
You'd think they might
be sensitized to it,
still all irritated and so
it might hurt even worse,
but no, it hurt less.
Then they did it again the next day
and the next.
By day 5 it hardly
hurt at all,
they didn't even get a
runny nose, no sneezing.
Came back the next week,
day ten and still nothing.
Sheesh, were they like
permanently numbed?
No, after a month or so the
desensitization wore off
and they were back
in agony whenever
they tried rubbing
it in their nose.
What the researchers think
is happening is that
the pain fibers, the nerves
that carry pain sensation,
dumped so much of the
pain neurotransmitter
called substance P
that they ran out.
Day after day of this the
nerves had exhausted
their stores and could no
longer transmit pain messages
until they made more
substance P from scratch,
which takes a
couple of weeks.
This gave researchers an idea.
There's a rare headache syndrome
called cluster headache.
It has been described as one
of the worst pains
humans experience.
Few, if any, medical disorders
are more painful.
It's nicknamed the
"suicide headache"
because patients often
consider taking
or have taken their
lives over it.
It's thought to be caused
by arterial dilation
putting pressure on the
trigeminal nerve in the face.
Treatments involve everything
from nerve blocks to
botox to surgery.
But hey, that same nerve
goes down to the nose.
What if we cause
the whole nerve
to dump all its
substance P?
"Preventative effect of repeated nasal
applications of capsaicin in cluster headache".
Same as before,
capsaicin in the nose
and by day 5 they could
hardly feel it any more.
Note though that these were
cluster headache sufferers
and so what was rated as an
8 or 9 on the pain scale
by the whimpy medical students
was like, maybe a 3 or 4
by those used to
the violence
of the cluster
headache attacks.
Having achieved
desensitization,
what happened to
their headaches?
Well cluster headaches
are one-sided headaches,
you only get pain on
one side of your head.
So those who had rubbed capsaicin
in the opposite nostril,
on the wrong side
of the head,
nothing happened.
They started out having
like 40 attacks a day
and a month later the headaches
were still going strong,
but those that rubbed the
capsaisin in the nostril
on the side of the head
where the headaches were,
cut the average number
of attacks in half.
And in fact half the
patients were cured!
The cluster headaches
were gone completely.
All in all 80%
responded,
at least equal
if not better
than all the current
therapies out there.
Finally today,
we discover the power of
powdered ginger for migraines.
Many successful herbal
treatments start like this.
Some doctor learns that
some plant has been used
by some ancient medical tradition,
like ginger for headaches
and figures, hey, they've
got patients with headaches
and since its just
some safe common spice
advises one of their migraine
patients to give it a try.
At the first sign of a migraine coming on,
the patient mixed a quarter teaspoon
of powdered ginger in some water,
drank it down, and poof, within a half hour
the migraine went away.
And it worked every time, no side-effects.
This is what’s called a case report,
which is really
just a glorified anecdote,
but case reports have
played an important role
in the history of medicine.
AIDS was first discovered
as a series of case reports.
Some young guy walks
into a clinic in Los Angeles
with a bad case of thrush
and the rest is history.
Or reports of an unusual side-effect
of a failed chest pain drug
leading to the billion
dollar blockbuster, Viagra.
Case reports may be the ‘lowest’
or ‘weakest’ form of evidence,
but they are often the
‘first line of evidence.’
That’s where everything begins.
So a report like this
isn’t helpful in and of itself,
but it can inspire researchers
to put it to the test.
The problem is, who’s going to fund it?
The market for migraine drugs
is worth billions of dollars.
A quarter teaspoon of powdered
ginger costs about a penny.
So who’d fund a study pitting ginger
versus the leading migraine drug?
No one...
...until now.
A double-blinded randomized
controlled clinical trial
comparing the efficacy
of ginger to sumatriptan,
also known as Imitrex,
one of the top-selling
billion dollar drugs in the world,
in the treatment of
migraine headaches.
They tried using just
one eighth of a teaspoon
of powdered ginger versus
a good dose of the drug.
And they both worked
just as well, just as fast.
Most started out in moderate
or severe pain before,
but after the drug or ginger,
ended up mild or pain free.
The same proportion of migraine
sufferers reported satisfaction
with the results either way,
and so as far as I’m
concerned ginger won,
not only because it’s a
few billion dollars cheaper
but because there were
significantly fewer
side-effects in the ginger group.
On the drug people reported dizziness,
a sedative effect,
vertigo and heartburn.
The only thing reported for
ginger was an upset tummy
in about 1 in of 25 people,
though taking a whole
tablespoon of ginger powder
at one time on an empty stomach
could irritate anyone’s tummy,
just as a note of caution.
Sticking to an eighth of a teaspoon
is not only up to 3000 times
cheaper than the drug,
but you’re probably less likely to
end up as a case report yourself
of people that have had a heart attack
or died after taking the drug.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books were
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of “How Not to Age”.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.